{
  "reference_number": "2072",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "I think the Climate Change Commission should have more than purer advisory. It's recommendations should become policy with the\n\n Caveat that the recommendation would need to be rejected by 75% of MPs for the recommendation not to proceed. This assumes\n that CCC (climate change commission) is appropriately balanced in membership and appropriately resourced with access to the best\n science & knowledge. The TOR would clearly be written along the lines of achieving the objectives that the government as agreed to\n\n both nationally & internationally and this to be achieved at least to economy in the broadest sense. The government with a 75% veto\n would be able to set context where recommendations could be deferred because of national calamity or similar."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "As a high performing low intensity pastoral farmer there are some real challenges in trying to manage Methane in particular. We will\n get gains on nitro s Oxide as we try to manage nitrogen losses. We need an increased science to help find solution(s) to CH4\n challenge. I believe that GMO's should be considered as part of solution and this something that CCC could evaluate. We as a nation\n\n should go hard on those gases where we have proven solutions and tackle the most challenging ones later. We do need to stabilise\n the short term gases because if they are allowed to increase this undermines the gains made in other areas."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": "The last option makes more sense as potentially it allows for the most effective use of the globes resources (in theory). My\n observation with any form of tradeable rights is that rather achieving the desired outcomes of reductions and efficient use of\n resources, they are often captured by those with the most capital at the expense of those less resourced potentially increasing the\n\n disparity in wealth between individuals and between nations. Rather than ICU's per se maybe the model should be that NZ'ers and\n NZ farmers could say provide money to say a UN fund that could plant trees and forests elsewhere thereby both creating\n\n employment and potentially wealth in those areas. i.e. a variation on ICU's model."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Yes but requiring a higher hurdle rate in government than just 50% to take the decision away from a purer party vote."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "Need to be able to adapt to change circumstance. I would much prefer to see the budgets fixed with a 75% hurdle for changes\n\nrequired. There can always be exceptional circumstances - famine - natural disaster - war."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "see above"
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Need to be able to collect real information on the real impacts of the legislation on the people as potentially the poorest people in the\n\ncommunity could be most disadvantaged if cost of fuel and food increase excessively. Question: how should an inflation resulting\nfrom the changes be handled by the Reserve Bank?"
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I agree with the functions but I do wonder if some decision making powers are not appropriate to keep the decisions from being too\npolitical but as said early a check always needs to be in place. I wonder how much further ahead had the government chief science\n\nadvisor had some decision making powers."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Agree with those attributes but there needs to be some linkage between CCC and various sectors Energy Local government,\n\nAgriculture horticulture etc."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "It should identify work & science streams that need happen for adaption."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Really appreciate the pro active way that engagement on this issue is being handled - congratulations"
    }
  ]
}
